with which for them to stand and not to fall, and he will be the light of the nations,
and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled. All who dwell on the earth will fall down and
worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5. The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless
haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison
of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment
in creation, the union of the scene and unseen
as made by God and experienced by mankind
to route his-
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, basheres of bail.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast and my co-host,
the very Reverend Doctor, Father Stephen D'Yan,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymick, not as many initials next to my name,
here in Amia's Pennsylvania, and we're live.
Don't give up, you can get there.
yet
five six masters degrees now. Five six. I have it. I haven't told you yet, but it looks like I might be getting another one this summer.
Okay, as one does on your way to your second PhD. So yeah, I mean you are going to die much younger than I am. So it is possible. I could catch up someday.
Probably see there you go. Probably. Yeah. So yeah. So we are live. And listen, if you're listening to us live, you can call us at 855 237 2346. That's 855 AF radio.
And you can talk.
us. And we're going to get your calls in the second half of the show and
Mattris Katruty will be taking your calls. In the great feast of the
offene, Jesus Christ is baptized in the Jordan River by the forerunner. It's
the inauguration of his public ministry, but it's a whole lot more. In previous
episodes, we've discussed baptism, as well as the great blessing of water, which
are of course both closely related to this feast, but tonight we're going to be
discussing the feast itself.
So it turns out
that Theophany has something to do with Adam, probably no big surprise. It might also not be a big
surprise to learn that it has something to do with water gods. But it may be a surprise to learn
that it also has something to do with the Canaanite Storm god, Bale. So what is that all about, Father?
I don't know, man, you brought it up. Oh, let me look it up real quick. Oh wait. Yeah, so yeah,
there is, so I don't know how constant.
the text of the great blessing of the waters is. But at least as it's currently done in the
adiocune archdiocese, there's this place of the text where you do this big long prayer
about all the accomplishments of Christ. And they just sort of tacked onto the end of
the prayer is, now as Endanger destroyed the worship of Bale.
Yes, right. We just thrown it there like Ed
And as everyone knows, right.
And it's sort of centrally to the great rest of the water, the celebration of the
offety is, oh, by the way, no more bail worship.
Right.
And so that's not the only place bail comes up.
Bill comes up with the Old Testament readings.
bail comes up other places as well.
So as you mentioned, we've done a couple episodes of the past.
We did talk about baptism.
We did episode on the great blessing of the waters.
And so the thing is the feast of theophany,
and we'll talk a little bit more about this
in the beginning of the second half,
being one of the most ancient celebrations
within Christianity.
Yeah, um, sort of the
There's a number of trajectories you can kind of take through it or I mean I
Angles for being especially for being so old. I do pity the poor fools that do not have the offening in their Christian life
So sad because it's such an amazing amazing feast. So yeah, come on you guys. Let's do the offening
Yeah, a piphony kind of is a weak sister
Right, like I mean, I like the Magi as much as the next guy, right
But it's just not the same.
They do have really cool names though.
Caspar, Melchior, Dauzare.
Those are all names.
Here's the beautiful thing about being orthodox in southern Louisiana.
You could both celebrate theophony and then eat kingcake.
Hey, you don't have to choose.
So yeah, so there's a lot of different angles to come in.
the feast from. And you alluded in your introduction, which it's sometime at the last minute, I'm
going to go in and like change your written introduction. See if I notice.
To see if you do a Ron Burgundy and just read whatever's there. Yeah.
So the audience will find out as well at some point in the indeterminate future.
But yeah, you alluded to a couple of those. This prevalence, these repeated mentions of Adam.
And these repeated references to bail.
And so while it may not immediately be apparent, it may be a little more apparent to long-time
listeners of the podcast.
They kind of have at least a vague idea of how those two are connected, right?
how Adam and Bale might be connected in the Hebrew scriptures in the Old Testament.
estimate. But that's what we're going to start by getting into. Right? So we're going
to talk a little bit about who bail is and then how he's connected to Adam. And then
that'll take us into our discussion of the feast of theophony and what's going on with
Christ baptism. I know there's somebody out there right now going it's but all. Yes,
I know.
Here's, okay, so here's the thing.
Let me discover this right now.
We're just coming this right now.
Because I know I've already said this many places,
right, that I think one of the cringiest things
in the world is what people refer to Jesus as Yeshua.
Yeah, or my favorite is when they add extra syllables
like Yahoo, Yahoo, Shua or whatever.
Well, yeah, but yeah.
It's like, don't, okay?
You're speaking English.
Right, there are English versions of these names.
Yes, yes.
And this even goes for our Greek friends.
I do not get this weird selectivity, right?
We're like, you know, the prophet Nathan is the prophet Nathan and the prophet Samuel is the prophet Samuel, but then all of a sudden we've got like a
Liest and elicious because we can't say Elijah and Elijah now.
Oh, man, we don't want to talk about petros, but we got to talk about Yakovos really guys shots are being fired. That's the one that really I don't get. Yeah, it's like and Peter, John Andrew Matthew Yakovos.
I don't know.
If you want to use all Greek names, cool.
I totally find with that.
Use all Greek names, right?
Or I prefer my preference.
I use all standard English pronunciations, right?
So I say bail.
I propose this question.
But you got to pick one man.
You can't just be bouncing around and like, you know.
Well, this day, but I'm going to say an error.
This one.
You know, right?
So yes, it is technically bought all two syllables.
They just technically aromac.
That's actually the aromac pronunciation, not the original phonetian pronunciation.
What is an original phonetian?
It's closer to bell.
So the the the Hellenization then is actually a little bit closer to that.
Yeah, the first A is sort of a schwa.
But I'll but I'll.
Yeah, and so that's why it is I'm getting shortened like in battle
Babylonian Debell and in some of the languages it gets certain to bell.
Yeah, and so while that is on one hand a word, right?
Yeah, it's just a common word.
Lord, yeah.
Lord, master or husband?
Yeah, sure.
Which already tells you something about the ancient Ereast, right?
So that is a title that was a title just used in general
Right. Yeah, it's a word that's used in common every day speech
It also becomes a title that gets attached
in the ancient Near East in the pagan world to a whole bunch of different
deities
Yeah, right so you could say by all and then
the name of a pagan god it also
Because we've talked about before, like Baal Paor in numbers being a good example, you
have the Baal of a particular place.
Yeah.
Right, to refer to a spirit, a God associated with that place.
But it shows up in surprising places, right?
If you've looked at the history of later-upinic Judaism, you've heard of the ball-shim-
Tove, right? You're like, why does he have bail in front of his
name? They're just using it to be master. Right. Right.
To refer to this rabbi, the way Christian churches, like in
Syriac churches, they use more or more, yep, which has basically
the same meaning or say in the or for the deco or right, whatever.
So I can have this many bail says, I don't really go too
Okay, here we go.
before we part of the rabbit hole.
What are the minor prophets?
There's raised where God says,
before you knew me as a ball,
but now you will know me as, right?
That's good.
And of course our 19th century German friends,
ah, see, there's the tell,
there's the one they miss to see.
Oh yes, our terrible editors strike again.
Yes, they use the worship bail.
And of course, it's before you knew me as Lord and Master.
Now you will know.
right, more intimate terms, right?
Oh, we have someone tuning in from Bavaria, from Munich actually.
So speaking of 19th century Germans, we have a 20th century German.
I'm hoping it's not a 19th century German.
It would be amazing if Hagle was somehow listening from some sort of vampiric appearance.
Yes.
Or, yeah, some kind of machine that allows them to hear broadcast signals through time.
The Glotesla would be involved somehow too, right?
Come up with a really good episode of Dr. Who here,
like if we worked on it.
So there is that general usage of the word,
but that name is also used as a proper name
for a particular God in certain cultures.
Yeah.
and probably that...
Not probably the the most significant culture that uses that name for a particular god biblically is
the Phoenician culture
To the immediate north right of
Judah and Israel and what's not on basically yeah and
And this is because this is where sort of the cross currents come in.
The bail.
who's being referred to with the Bible is that bail. The bail of the bail cycle that we've
talked about a few times on the show that was found to do garret, who garret is in what's
now Lebanon. A bail cycle was found there. That's the bail we're talking about. Right?
So not any of the other various bail, bail is used in the plural in places in the Old Testament,
But we're referring to this one.
particular one. The ban. Yeah, the Phoenician. Bale, who is the son of L, right? And similar
to how Bale could just be Lord or Master, L is also just the word for God, right? There's
a lot of people probably already know, but that word is also used within, to refer to
a particular God who is the father of Bill.
So we've talked before.
four on the show several times about the bail cycle and about bail and the course of that.
And bail is very exploits at which he totally wins several battles and then reacts as if he lost them.
And we've talked about how in a couple of places in the Old Testament,
that that
Bale's story as it is told by the Phoenicians and other neighboring countries, and as it is told in the Bale cycle,
get sort of reworked or corrected. The record gets corrected by the Hebrew Scriptures, which identify the Bale figure with the devil.
What?
with the one who comes to be called the devil. And so, bail, right, we're not going to go through
everything in super detail that we've gone over in the past again, but if there are bail, is sort of,
the rebellious son of L. And L is this sort of remote, most high god, sort of a prototypical example of
of it.
We've talked about this before on the show.
How within pagan cultures,
sort of parallel to the story that's told
in the story of the Tower of Babel,
there's observable phenomenon in cultures across the world
that whoever was seen as the most high god
above the other gods kind of drifts off into the background.
And it is sort of the lower gods usually provided
provided over, presided over by a God who
the scene is being the son of that most high God are the ones who are worshiped.
Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah.
Obvious parallel like in North culture, Odin is considered to be the most high God, but
you know, it's Thor that is really, as we know, from archaeology and stuff, is the one who's
really being worshiped a lot. Right. Right. And the same thing is true, though, we're less aware of it
Unless you dig into like direct sources like
re play-doh for example. And you read Hesseyid,
Krowness is still lurking in the background in Greek religion.
With Zeus as his son, right? So Plato talks about the age of Krowness and these things,
like sort of before he withdrew. So he's still lurking in the background there, but it's his son Zeus
who's who's who everybody is paying attention.
right? You don't find, I mean there, there are a few here, there, but you don't find primarily temples to
Kronus, right? Right. You find temples to Zeus. And the same thing is true here. You don't find a lot of
temples to L. You find temples to bail. And there are depictions of L within those, right, of Bale's father,
who's just depicted as this sort of old man.
And in the bail cycle and other places,
He really is depicted as this kind of useless old man.
Hmm.
Um, we've talked before I know about Bale's sister wife,
threatening to crack his skull open if he didn't make Bale a temple, right?
Right. Um, like he's not, he's not portrayed as sort of this majestic
father of the God's most high god figure. It's again, it's like this, this
daughter of a gold pool and bails the one who's made
things happen. Right? So there's this element of rebelliousness even between
Bale and L. Even though Bale's rebellion in the Bale cycle actually is what makes L
technically the most high god. There's it's not he's not this submissive
dutiful sort of sun carrying out L's will on the earth or something quite the opposite.
Yeah.
And of course we've talked about that sort of revolution that previously
Yom, the sea, and Nahar, the river, right, were the most high God and his son
respectively. So it's King Yom and Prince Nahar, right? And they get
unseeded in this succession myth by Bales Rebellion, other things that figure
prominently in that story are his defeat.
of Lothan, aka Leviathan, the great sea monster, right?
Because these are the symbols of chaos, right?
And then Bale is depicted as the one
because he is a storm god who rides upon the clouds
of heaven who has wheels of the thunderbolt,
right, it's a symbol of power.
All of these things, right?
So we've talked about all that before.
multiple times I think. So what we want to now talk about a little more this time is we're going to
comment this from another angle. And we're going to talk about this from the perspective not so much
of the myth of bail, the bail cycle, the bail story and compare your contrasting that with the
story of the devil.
we have before, but we're going to come at this more from the perspective of bail worship,
right? The phenomenon of bail worship in the Levant, right? In the ancient Near East as it affects
Israel, right? Because, you know, our starting point there, it's the worship of bail that ceases,
right? Worship not just, not just, you know, people forget the stories or whatever, although that
That does happen, right?
Right. Eventually the actual stories get forgotten until the 20th century.
Because it was the ritual worship that was keeping those stories alive. Yeah.
And so now it's mythology. Now we look back on it and dissect it, but it's not alive anymore.
And so one way to take into that is to sort of briefly revisit those two passages that I mentioned.
one of them in particular but we can
mention the other one, where the prophets, the Old Testament prophets, make this connection
between the devil and bail and the context of those.
So the one mainly we want to focus on here from this other angle is Ezekiel chapter 28.
This is the one that is framed as an oracle against the king of tire.
T.Y. Ari, not the king of tires.
Yeah, not your local tires for 60 bucks down the road.
That's right.
Yeah.
Discount tires.
Although, you know, it's, it is T.Y.
R.E. The city is that right?
But if you're in the UK, that is how you spell tire like on, on your car with the Y.
So the whole of our British listeners are like, what?
What are we?
Definitely need to disambiguate for them.
Yeah.
Um.
So within that oracle, and I believe we mentioned this when we've gone through it before, there's this
differentiation that's made between the king of tire, the mellak of tire in Hebrew and the prince of
or SAR. And that word, SAR, this translated prince, really is a different thing than KING.
Right. So the ancient Near East, the word king carries with it, as we've talked about many times,
the idea of frankly divinity. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right. You know, the God king, right, that whole idea,
whereas the word here that's translated prints can mean like,
Chiefed in leader. Yeah, the big ball of a group. Right. Um, head man.
is really the core of it, right? Is it that it's like the head man, right? The guy in charge, right?
And as I believe we've talked about before, that differentiation is important because
there is this divine figure who fell from among the stones and Eden, right?
Called the King of Tire, who's being talked about sometimes. And then there's this Prince of Tire
who's talked about in very material human.
terms, which is the human guy who calls himself the king of tire.
Yeah. Right. So that language is being used to sort of
demote from the perspective of your Phoenician worldview, to demote the king of tire from divinity.
Number one, and then number two, to say that the spiritual power who they're worshiping is bail,
The spiritual power that stands behind
Tyre is
This spirit that seeks the destruction of humankind who's already gone one round with God and lost very badly
right and
So the prophecy then is talking about how
The Prince of Tyre right the human kit will follow if he keeps following Bale he will follow Bale
L.
Right.
Into the underworld.
So to talk a little bit more about Tyre and Sidon because they come up frequently in the
Old Testament and even a couple of times in the New Testament.
These are massively important cities in the ancient world.
We haven't talked a lot about Phoenicia.
We've talked a lot about Babylon.
We've talked a lot about some other civilizations, Sumer and Akad and Egypt.
Yeah.
Because we haven't really talked about Phoenicians yet.
these are cities.
up on the Lebanese sea coast because there's still there. Yeah, yeah, there's still there.
The Phoenicians are sea traders. This is their big thing. They found Carthage,
like Carthage Indian Empire eventually. Yeah, we have to just abiguate here.
Yeah, right. A little bit. Because if people think about the Phoenicians,
right, and even I don't think about the Phoenicians every day, Roman Empire sure but Phoenicians know.
They tend to think about Hannibal, Carthage, the Punic Wars with Rome.
Yeah, with all the other parts.
Obviously, that's much later.
This is way right.
Yeah, yeah.
There's a much earlier stage, right?
So this is the period when Carthage is like a trading outpost in North Africa.
Because what Mediterranean trade meant at this point in history, right, they didn't have
the capacity to sail across the Mediterranean.
at least not on purpose. No, it was always coastal sailing. You could get blown off course and get
lucky, right? Maybe. But the intent was always you went around the coast, which means you had to
have ports and stops sort of all along the coast because you have to put your boat into birth
every so often. Right. And to keep right then from those trade ports,
Caravan
and so it would follow trade routes all over the place.
So all through North Africa, up into various parts of Europe,
moving eastward from what's now Lebanon
across the fertile crescent, Egypt, all of these places.
And so Venetia is really the first empire,
not the first empire that does trade,
because we've talked here for about
like homerobs, Babylonian empire,
the Rachel.
Babylonian Empire is doing trade all over not just what we think of as the known world at the time
but I mean we've talked about how they had things going from Afghanistan to Cyprus to yeah right
but they are the first empire that is an empire of trade yeah it's not really based on like
conquering big tracts of land right they're not going in it's not about conquering your neighbors
like the previous and frankly
most of the subsequent empires are. Right. It is at this point, especially, right. They later will
see that's why I wanted to differentiate. By the time Carthage really becomes their focal capital,
you have a Phoenician empire in North Africa that has become a military power. There's obvious from
Hannibal. Right. And so things have changed. But at this stage, it is purely a trade empire. Yeah,
they're just super good.
merchants. Yeah. So more like the forangi than the klingons. Right. Like. Yeah. And that's,
I mean, and this is why they have to invent the alphabet, right? Because you need written records
if you're going to really do trade. Right. And and and and a means and a means to communicate. Right.
Because people don't really like in in revised kuneiform languages.
Like the revised ones.
that they teach you first if you decide you want to learn to read Kadeh Form. There are
between 80 and 90 symbols that you have to learn. Yeah and they're not easy to make. Like each
one takes multiple little indentations in clay. In clay and that's your only writing medium.
Yeah. Alphabet is just a kid. Kadeh Form on parchment. Yeah. Yeah exactly. I mean alphabet is
is just way easier to use, much more sort of fungible as it were.
in terms of text. Right. And can be adapted to other languages. Right. Meaning famously,
the Greeks can take it and take their spoken language and write it using the Phoenician alphabet.
Yes. With a couple of adaptations for sounds they don't have. Right. So and that's, you know,
So, for folks who don't know.
right? In most aromatic languages, you make something definite. You put the definite article
in front of it, the, by adding an olive and A. That's not totally accurate, but...
That's like an Arabic, there's a...
It's a simplification, right? Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You put it in a sound, right, in a letter a la if it's an a sound, roughly. At the end of the word,
Right. And so this is where even the names of the Greek letters come from. So you have
all of a becomes alpha. Yeah.
Bait a dollar a becomes delta. Right. And on and on. So if you know the Greek alphabet,
you know some Semitic languages. That's how you get from one to the other. But yeah.
So it's because it's a trade empire. If you have an empire of conquest, you just sort of
impose your language upon the...
Right. The people you've just conquered, it's like, well, you better learn, right?
Or you just use it to exclude them. Yeah, but in this case, they want their money.
They want their money. Yes.
But with a trade empire where you're wanting to make partners, partnerships, and ongoing
cooperative partnerships, right? Communication becomes key. That's part of what leads to
Okay, the alphabet. But you can see...
within that ethos then, how that connects to their worship of Bale. Yeah, because Bale is the guy who beats up the God of the seas.
The sea, right? Yeah, the caves controls the seas, which is where they're making their living. And Bale is a storm god.
Super important for sailors.
And storms are what you're worried about when you're out there
with a boat full of trade goods, all the sea, right?
So, this is why bail becomes, and you've got bail in the positive, quote unquote, positive
sense, like in the bail cycle, being praised for his defeat, his conquering of the sea in
the river, right?
And then on the negative side, he's a storm god, you want to appease him.
So he doesn't smack you around with thunderbolts and winds and rain and sink your battleship.
So um...
There is this integral relationship between their worship and their culture, right, in this regard.
And so, Ezekiel's prophecy, you can go read, is equal 28 again. We won't read it all right now.
But you can go read it again. You can see how this is intertwined together, right?
intertwined together for them. There's not this separation between.
Well, like this is our religion, and then we have our business dealings over here and
then politics.
And then these other things, right, this is all intertwined for them.
And so the oracle against them, right, calling them to repent, that oracle, it's all intertwined
within it.
The other place that we'll just mention, if people I go back to and look at where the figure
of bail and...
or at least a very bail, a bail is brought into parallel with the devil as Isaiah 14.
Yeah, that's the the Lucifer passage, basically.
Right. Yeah.
Where he's yeah, in Latin where he says he's going to set his throne above the stars and so forth.
Right. Right.
So the way in which
Bale primarily appears into
terms of volume of text dealing with bail, right, in the Hebrew Bible in the Old Testament.
It's actually not about the devil, right?
You may have noticed that there's not a ton about the devil himself in the Hebrew Bible
or the Old Testament, right?
There's some, we just gave two examples, right?
And we're going to come back to another example that you're probably all expecting.
here in a little bit. But the primary place where bail comes up is actually, again, in the context of
bail worship and bail worshipers. And because this is actually on the ground, this is a live concern,
it's part of life. Right. Right. And that comes into play through the Omride dynasty in the northern
kingdom of Israel. And we need to, I feel the need at least to constantly reframe for us
The history of Israel is actually presented in the Old Testament and actually was in the world.
In the sense that I know I want to go down this road again, but as we've talked about it in our episodes on how to read the Bible,
the knee jerk reaction to sort of Protestant...
the denial of the historicity of the Old Testament was this knee-jerk
response of
Know the Old Testament is objective history
Right the objective there being the problem right it is modern history it is objective modern scientific history
right
and
It's clearly it's clearly not
But what do I mean by that?
How does that affect this?
Folks who haven't studied the ancient Near East and the archaeology in the history
probably think that the most famous and prominent
King of Israel in the world was Solomon
Right
especially if you
grew up or first read the Bible within that kind of context where it's like no this is
like this literal objective scientific modern history.
that is simply not true.
Yeah, that's not what archaeological records shows.
It's not what we actually find in the records of other cultures.
Right.
So...
That's not the reality.
But that's not a problem.
If you actually understand what's going on in what we now call the historical books,
what we're originally called the former prophets.
in the Hebrew Bible and the Christian testament. And that's that we are being given a very
deliberate perspective. God's perspective on these people and these times and what happens.
And we're reminded of that over and over and over again. Right? Pretty much every king
at the end of the description is, as for everything else he did,
Yeah, is it not written in the
Is it not written in the annals of the kings of Israel?
right? Because they had annals, they had chroniclers, right? Who were writing down all the great
things that all those kings did, right? People kept track of that stuff. Yeah, if you're looking for
the big list of all the things that these guys did, it's written somewhere else. That's not what this
book is about. Yeah, that's not what it's about, right? And Exhibit A of this is actually the
Omride Dynasty that we're about to talk about in more detail. Omri, who's the founder of the Omride
by Dynasty.
who basically comes to power in the northern kingdom of Israel over the 10 times through assassination
is simply the most prominent king of Israel or Judah in the eyes of the surrounding world.
Yeah.
Archaeologically, uh, uh,
Israel's referred to as bait omray, the House of Omray.
pretty much for the rest of the time it exists, which isn't long.
Yeah, let me read. I think it's important to reiterate that too.
There was a political entity called Israel in the ancient Near East
for a grand total of about 270 years.
Yeah, it wasn't like millennia long.
Yes. Other than that 270 year period,
3000 years ago, the only other time there's been a nation in the world called
Israel has been very recently. Yeah. We have to frame that, right? Judah lasted
a little longer after the split. Yeah, right. But even if you add up, if we start
with Saul, right? And we end with the Babylonian exile, right? When Judah is taken
to x.
No more kings. Yeah, we're dealing with a little over 400 years. Right? So like the US is getting into this kind of territory in terms of how long it's existed.
Right. It's not like say France or England. Right. It existed for millennia.
Yeah.
Excuse me.
Oh, so Omri is Omri is,
the king of the northern kingdom. He's not a yeah he's not a Davidic king. Right. But
Omri despite being super important right you can see his name on monuments at the British Museum
right and it's not his name because he made the monuments. It's like monuments of his descendants
as king you know Jeyu from the house of Omri coming and paying tribute to the Assyrians.
Yeah.
Right. He's the one who, and this part is recorded in the Bible, he's the one who basically
begins the establishment of the capital of the Northern Kingdom at Samaria.
The Bill of Samaria. He shows up in 1 Kings chapter 16.
Yeah, and then he himself. Yeah, himself. You know, it's a few more than that.
16 and 16 through and then he dies in verse 28.
And then you go.
Yeah, then you get a.
After that.
Right.
So he gets 12 versus basically saying he's bad.
We could we could bad buys the hill where Samaria's built.
Very bad.
Right.
And as for the other things he did, are they not written?
That's 27.
Right.
Whereas, you know, David, where we finally found a couple places where his names are mentioned
because his name is mentioned because
tell then all of our 19th century German friends had assured us he was like King Arthur and was mythical.
Obviously has the better part of two books of the Bible about him. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. Solomon obviously has a great deal more. Right.
So those who are important in the sight of God and those who are important in the sight of the world.
not always the same people, right? And the Scriptures are talking to us about the former,
not the latter, right? So, Omri, though, is this this massive figure who really establishes the
dynasties before his in the northern kingdom, generally last two generations? And then when I say
assassination. It's not just O somebody assassinates the kid.
and then takes over, you had to assassinate the King's whole family. Yeah. Right.
You had to kill the King, all his wives, all the children of those wives. Right. Right.
Because otherwise someone could show up and say, Hey, as a rival claim it. So you had
destroy that dynasty so that it could not go on. Right. What?
of the female descendants of this line,
Atholaya is gonna try to do that in Judah,
gonna try to wipe out the Davidic line that way.
In her role as Queen Mother in the Southern Kingdom of Judah.
But so Omri, part of how he establishes himself
and establishes the Northern Kingdom of Israel
is by making trade agreements, right?
There are a decent amount of natural resources in the northern kingdom, but not on par with Venetia.
Whether we're talking about Cedar wood or whether we're talking about their shipping empire and this kind of thing.
But Israel occupies this important place in the Levant at the end of the fertile crescent where people going to Egypt, right.
It's a long trade routes.
And so this gives him opportunities to make deals and to make a lion.
to bolster the Northern Kingdom's power.
And one of those major alliances,
the most major of those alliances,
because Ahab, his son is gonna be his heir,
he marries Ahab to the daughter of the King of Siden.
And her name is Jezebel.
Yes, her name is Jezebel.
So I should mention we mentioned tire,
Sident.
We're sort of the twin capitals of Phoenicia at this point.
I say twin capitals because Tyre was at this point in history on an island.
Yeah, it's a peninsula now.
Yes, but it was on an island.
And so it was the military cap of capital because it was obviously very defensible.
It's kind of hard to lace each to an island, especially when you're competing against a naval power.
and a shipping power.
Siden was on the mainland.
So that was sort of the business capital, right,
where people were most of the time, right,
when they weren't under attack.
Tire was considered to be unconquerable
until Alexander the Great conquered it,
which he did by turning it into a peninsula.
Right, yeah.
by getting a lot of slave
to build him a land bridge.
Yeah, and the two cities, by the way, everybody, are just about, if you're driving, about 35 minutes apart, like Siden is up the coast, and then Tyre, you can see, if you look at a modern map, you can see how it sticks out into the water.
Yeah. So at this time a nice fellow named Ethobaol is
is the the priest king of Sidon,
Jezebel, and that bell is Bale-Bal.
Yeah, yeah.
She's got a theophoric name.
A name with a god tucked away in there.
Yeah, and eto ball is actually known from other places.
His name is found in Greek chronicles.
This is a sort of known guy,
Amanda mentions him and calls him ether.
Bollos, who he says was a priest of a starte who, if you remember, is Bale's sister wife.
So, he is relatively known from other places.
he should king Jezebel's name is probably fiddled with.
So...
We've talked before about, I think, on the show about how the ancient Israelites and
Hebrew speakers liked to fiddle with other people's titles and names.
Yeah.
So you've been insult them, typically.
Yes.
So there's a king who's an enemy of Israel in the Old Testament named Kushner Shatayim
from Mahana Harayim.
I feel like this to be the beginning of a rap or something by you.
Yeah, see that?
that five times fast.
Mahana Haryam, right?
Mahana Haryam, you might have picked up Nihar, right?
Mahana Haryam is a way referring to Mesopotamia
between the rivers.
But Kusher and Resatayam is,
we can be pretty sure not what his mom named him,
because it means sort of double dark evil one.
Probably not what you name your kid, right?
I mean, maybe today some people would,
But, yeah, not.
not so much in the past. So this is very clearly like he had some name similar to that and
he was fiddled with it a little to mean that and that's what they called him.
We've talked about how the title the Phoenician title of Baal Zabool, which means like great Lord Bale,
or High Lord Exalted Bale. They turned into Baal Zabub, Lord of the Flies.
Yeah, just you know.
In other words, Lord of the stuff that flies like to land on congregate about wink wink. Yeah, say no more
So that they did this so
It looks like Jezebel
Right because Jezebel means in Hebrew means something like where is bail?
Yeah, where's your guy? Yeah, where's bail?
Now
Yeah, I
My surmise is that there are different people who have different views of this because, you know, journal articles have to be written and dissertations have to be published.
But I think it's the fiddling is it was probably something like bail is there is bail the place of bail the place where bail is something like that was her actual name and they changed it to where is he.
also worth noting though, as we mentioned with the different uses of the word
all this can also mean where is your husband? Right. And in terms of the story of A-hab,
who is not the one who wears the pants in the family, shall we say throughout
what we see in the scriptures about A-hab, there may be something there too.
you, also worth thinking about.
St. Fautini, the Samaritan woman, the woman from Samaria, who Christ says, where's your husband?
Yeah, yeah.
And if he was speaking in Aramaic, what would he have said, right?
Yeah.
So you think about that too.
There's a free sermon for after Paska to all the priests listening.
There you go, guys.
Latch onto that and run with it. Okay
Okay.
St.Photini is the anti-Jesabel.
So I mean, I think it's popular use, even if you haven't read the story of Elijah and
they have a Jezebel in detail the scriptures, you probably have the idea that Jezebel,
referring to someone as age as a belt. It's a bad thing.
So, but this is because of her in the scriptures, she earns this.
So what concretely happens, Ahab as the heir of Omriga is married to her, and then when
he becomes king, she is now the queen.
So before this in Israel, the religion that's being practiced is the religion that was set
up by Jared Bome's son of knee bat.
Yeah.
Yeah, he takes, you know, remember everybody he's the one who sets up the golden calves and says,
you can worship the golden day. Yeah, using these things. And it's, it's become so like iconic
in the, in the Old Testament that worshiping Yahweh with golden calves is referred to as
the sin of Jeroboam, son of Nabat. Yeah. Over and over. Yes. Yes. You have just a category of
of abominations named after you, grats.
Nice.
This is why there are no
kids named Jeroboam running around in your church. The only reason. Because people love that name,
but no, he was a bad guy. Time until someone starts yelling on Twitter that there's a St. Jeroboam.
What, what do you give it? In somebody's Photoshop and icon. Anyway,
So, Jerebov sets up this state religion.
essentially of Catholic worship, which is
nominally still worshipy Yahweh, but as
embodied they believed
within these two golden calves. One at Bethel, one at Dan, because
there's nothing but good things to say about Dan in the Bible.
But Dan was the northern end, the very northern end of the
northern kingdom and Bethel was the southern end.
So that's why they're at either end.
So there's theoretically one nearer to you.
And with that came a whole series of feasts,
other than the feasts prescribed by the Torah,
because we're doing worship other than the worship prescribed by the Torah.
And so it's sort of this synchrotistic,
we're gonna say we're worshiping Yahweh, the God of Israel,
but we're gonna just do paganism,
Just inserting his name instead of
or whomever, right? And so with the coming of Jezebel to the throne, right, she is going to want to
shift this further, right? So there's already within the Bale worship of Finesha, the idea of the
the catholic bail, the bull bail that we've talked about a little bit on the show.
that we have to talk about carefully.
Let the listener understand go look it up for yourself.
Right.
So there is this bull calf element.
And we sometimes forget again we read or we've gotten a cliff notes version at some point of the divided kingdom of Northern Kingdom of Israel, the Southern Kingdom of Judah.
and we don't realize
that like not only were they separate, but for the couple hundred years that the Northern
Kingdom existed, they were perpetually at some level of cold or hot war with Judah.
That there was active hostility. So not just Atholaya, who I mentioned earlier,
who tried to wipe out Big Monarchy, but of course the zero Ephraimite war,
where the Northern Kingdom
teamed up with the Aramians, the Syrians, to attack Judah.
Right.
The whole purpose for Jeroboam of setting up those calves was he didn't want his
people going to Jerusalem to worship at the temple.
Yeah, it gives it gives power to Jerusalem.
It also brings frankly tourist money, you know.
Right.
So again, it's all intertwined.
Right, you can't pull these things apart.
They're all intertwined in the engineering.
And so this enmity is sort of a religious thing too.
So from the perspective of now this powerful Omride dynasty,
Jezebel wanting to solidify her power, very easy move is, right,
why are we still calling this God of worship?
They get the calves.
Yahweh, why don't we just worship bail there?
Right?
because after
always the God being worshiped in Judah, who we don't like, and the prophets of
Yahweh are causing trouble all the time in the northern kingdom, denouncing the
worship of the golden calves, denouncing the kings, right, proclaiming doom on
the last two dynasties that got wiped out, right? And remember from the
from the pagan mindset which Jessabelle firmly had.
Right. It was not a question. A prophet, she would have thought of prophets more like bail
them, right?
A bailer, remember who got sort of the or who gets hired to curse Israel by the gig of Moab.
Right.
So it's not that those previous two dynasties were doomed because the God who created the heavens
of the earth told them they were doomed for their disobedience, right?
Yeah, for me, for most pagans, that's not a thing.
No, it was these representatives of this other God put the curse, put a curse, put the whammy,
right, on those rulers, right? And so this is why not only does she start converting all of these
high places, including the golden calves into shrines to bail, but she starts mass occurring every
profit of Yahweh she can.
find right because they're the threat to her and her husband's power right and
their dynasty and their rule. So this is the backdrop for the Elijah story.
Yep. This that we just described is what's going on in the background, literally of the
Elijah story. And if you were at a yes, I said Elijah, deal with it.
Anyway.
So I could say Eliahu or I'm not even sure how exactly I pronounced it.
Yeah, that's Eliahu is roughly in Hebrew or Elias in Greek or etc. Right.
We all know it's same name or Louis.
I could be French.
Louis.
Oh man.
St. Louis.
Um, but yes, Elijah.
Um, this is the backdrop.
Right.
And if you go back and read the story of Elijah with this in your mind that this is
What's going on?
things start to click and make sense in new ways. Right? Like it it is a very different
right experience. Right? And so you know the Elijah story in terms of this
contest between him and the prophets of Bale and Jezebel's Bale worship of
course, Mount Carmel is this big apex of that conflict.
right? But we know from reading the rest of uh,
second kings that uh, or fourth kingdoms that there's not this mass repentance in the northern
kingdom after about normal. They do not turn their hearts back to the one. They don't all say,
oh, Elijah was right. We've been worshipping the wrong god. We've been doing this all wrong. We
need to all start going to the temple in Jerusalem, right? That doesn't. I mean, he's he's
popular in the moment.
you know Yahweh is God, Yahweh is God, right? But yeah, it's it's easy to get people to
get excited in the moment. See Palm Sunday. But that often doesn't lead to anything good.
And so because there's there's not this mass repentance, there's this changing, of course,
of the Northern Kingdom, right?
Bale is the Spirit.
Right that that the people are following
Right that is leading them and so he leads them to destruction
Right and the northern kingdom
Gets wiped out
right
because
And again the northern kingdom getting wiped out
Think about what we've been talking about this isn't just like oh they did a lot of bad stuff and eventually it was too much bad stuff
Yeah, it's not just.
they were following this spirit who promoted lust and bad sinful things. This is they actively
hated Yahweh, the God of Israel. Yeah, they became the enemies of God. Like they went full pagan.
They hated Yahweh, they hated Judah and wanted to destroy it. They hated the promises that were
were made to the line of David and wanted to destroy it.
In defiance of God.
Like this is...
They literally, yeah, made themselves God's enemies by their own choice, right?
Despite these calls to repentance. Elijah isn't the last prophet God sent to them
either. He kept sending them prophets, right? But they did not. And they killed some
of those prophets. So, right, that's that's one later Nexus point. And that's
That's laying important groundwork, right?
For where, where we're going to go?
talking about the offening. So the other little piece we need to do here in the first half
before we move on is remember the other thing, Adam. And with Adam, there is a place where he has
a run-in with the devil, right? Genesis 3. Yes, exactly. And it's not just another run-in,
but this is as we've talked about before on the show several times.
This is the same story that's being told in Isaiah 14 and
Ezekiel 28. Same story was being told from a third perspective, right?
In terms of how the devil fell.
Yeah, and remember everybody, the serpent gets thrown out of the garden.
So this is the devil being kicked out of paradise into the underworld.
Heaven yeah into the underworld where he's gonna eat
the dead. Yeah. He's going to become the eater of the dead. Sorry Michael Crite.
Right. And so we've talked about how, right, the motivator of this is this envy,
this jealousy, this envy. This is everywhere in the church, Father's.
This jealousy and envy that he had toward Adam over Adam's destiny.
in Christ, right, over his destiny, what we call theosis, right, that Adam, humanity, was going to end up being greater than the angelic beings, including him.
Right. And this is what brings about this fall. This is what brings about this
treachery him wanting to lead humankind to destruction. As we've talked about
before
Right. Pose it again. Okay. So the devil wants to get God to stop being God and to be
God himself. What's step one? Yeah, not not a thing everybody. This is not a thing that's
metaphysically ontologically possible. Yeah. Right. But what he can do is he can attack and
trying to destroy the fellow creature of God of which he is just.
us. Right. And the the the core of probably the question, I think you would agree with me
Father Andrew. At least go along with me for the sake of the show. Okay. The question we get the
most often addressed to the show. We had to pick one question the most often is always what how come
Some humans can rip.
and angels can.
Yes, that is correct.
That is the most common question.
Yes, I don't know why.
We've entered it a thousand times,
but it's something that's really hard to wrap your mind around
I think is what it is.
I think so, and, and, I think they're asking the question
from the wrong perspective.
Because I think the question usually gets asked,
and this is not a condibation of anyone who has asked it this way.
Right. No. Not just a...
Let's think about this a second. I think it's asked for the perspective of mechanism.
Yeah, because I think people think of holiness and sin or sin and repentance as simply equal and
opposite movements of the will. Like it's a decision I made. Right. Right. And so it's a how is it
that? Yeah. I can change my mind. Why can't I just change my mind? To what mechanism does a human
have recourse that an angel does not.
Right.
And so we'll give the answer about
a material changeable body, I don't think people find that satisfactory because they don't
find it satisfactory as mechanism.
But as we've talked about many times on other theological issues, mechanism is never the
right way to come into theological question.
The actual answer to why humans can repent and angels can't, right, is...
Because the sin of the angels was an attempt to destroy man.
Hmm, therefore God gives man away out of that destruction.
Right?
Because otherwise, if God did not give humans the capacity to repent, the devil would have won.
It'll be a peric-
victory. Yeah, right? While we're talking about the punic
horse, it would be a pure victory. Um, because he still would have
headed up in the underworld, but he would have headed up in the
underworld, not only with other fallen spiritual beings, but
with all of humanity, mission accomplished humanity destroyed.
That's why God gives humans a chance to repent. That's the
actual answer.
mechanism, I can't tell you. Right? Don't know what it's like to be an angel. Right?
But that's the reason. That's why humanity gets the chance to repent. Because the repentance
and salvation of humanity is how the devil is ultimately defeated. So, in the way this
So, in the way this...
The way this is expressed though in the text of Genesis 3, as we've talked about before,
is this issue of garments of skin, right, mortal flesh, right, that provide that capacity
for repentance, right.
And even though it's not explicit in the way people might like it in the text of Genesis
3 that Adam is repent, there's a key thing to understand
it on.
understanding early Christianity and second-time Judaism, as we've talked about before, is that
Adam is not the archetypal sinner.
No, canis.
For Jewish people in the first century AD, canis.
Sorry, Calvinus.
Adam and the difference between the two, there are several.
the differences in the curses, right? And Genesis 3 and 4.
But what those are taken to signify ultimately is the fact that Adam is repentant and can't
it's not. And as the figure of Cain gets elaborated, not just in his genealogy, but as that genealogy
gets interpreted, he doubles down. He gets worse and teaches his descendants to be even worse, right?
whereas Adam is seen as not only given this capacity for repentance, but as as
is repent.
repentant and there's a text that will read a little bit here to finish off the
first half called the Life of Adam and Eve that likely it was written in the
first century AD but is a pre-Christian Jewish text meaning it was probably
literally written during Christ's life under His birth before His baptism. It is
likely where this was actually.
originally composed, we don't have the Hebrew original, we've got a lot of different translations
in other languages. We quoted from it before about something else, a section that's not
going to be in the part that we're reading right now. But we'll close with this because
this is sort of from that period sort of a very full meditation and collection of traditions
about the repentance of Adam.
Yeah, and we should emphasize this is an apocryphal text.
reading it's yeah, so look for it if you're Bible. Yeah, it's yeah, it's but it is a an edifying text that
you can read at home or or you know on a podcast and you know, Reese in it as you said it's a collection of
traditions. Yeah, so this is from the life of Adam and Eve and this is the part that's about
their repentance. So it starts out this way. Eve said to Adam, my Lord, tell me what
penitence and how long should I perform it, less perhaps we place on ourselves a
labor which we cannot endure, and he not hear our prayers. And the Lord turned his
face from us because we did not fulfill what we promised. My Lord, how much
penitence are you thinking of doing since I brought labor and tribulation upon
you? Adam said to Eve, you cannot do as much as I but do as much so that you
might be saved. For I will do 40 days of fasting. You, however, arise and go to
The Tigris.
river and take a stone and stand upon it in the water up to your neck in the depth of the river.
Let not a word go forth from your mouth since we are unworthy to ask of the Lord,
for our lips are unclean from the illicit and forbidden tree.
Stand in the water of the river for 37 days.
I, however, will do 40 days in the water of the Jordan.
Perhaps the Lord will have mercy on us.
Eve walked to the tiger's river and did just as Adam told her.
Likewise, Adam walked to the Jordan river
and stood up.
upon a rock up to his neck in the water.
Adam said,
I say to you water of the Jordan, mourn with me and separate from me all swimming creatures
which are in you, let them surround me and mourn with me, let them not lament for themselves,
but for me, for they have not sinned, but I.
Immediately all living things came and surrounded him in the water of the Jordan stood from that
hour not flowing in its course.
18 days past, then Satan grew angry, and transfigured himself into the
the brilliance of an angel, and went off to the Tigris River to Eve. He found her weeping,
and then the devil himself, as if mourning with her, began to weep and said to her,
"'Come out of the water and rest and weep no longer. Seize now from your sadness and lamenting.
Why are you uneasy? You and your husband Adam.'" The Lord God has heard your lamenting and
accepted your penitence. All of us angels have pleaded for you, praying to the Lord,
and he sent me to lead you forth from the water and to give you the nourishment which you had in
and paradise and for which...
you have grieved, now therefore come out of the water, and I will lead you to the place
where your food is prepared. Hearing this, Eve believed him, and went out of the water
of the river. Her flesh was like grass from the water's coldness. When she had come out,
she felt the ground, but the devil stood her up and led her to Adam. When Adam saw her
and the devil with her, he cried out with tears, saying, Oh, Eve, oh, Eve, where is the
work of your penitence. Have you, how have you again been seduced by our adversary?
through whom we were alienated from the dwelling of paradise and spiritual happiness.
When he heard this, she knew that it was the devil who had persuaded her to go out from the river,
and she fell in her face on the ground and a grief was double, as was her wailing in lamentation.
She cried out saying,
Whoa to you devil! For what reason do you fight against us? What concern do you have with us?
What have we done to you that you should persecute us so grievously? Why does your malice extend to us?
Did we ever take your glory from you or cause you to be
without honor. Why do you persecute us? So enemy impiously and jealous on to death.
And it goes on. But that's the exit. This is a piece of it. Yeah. Yeah. There was some before
that. There's some after. But indeed. Yeah. So but hearing that, some elements to keep in mind.
Right. The tradition of Adams repentance connects it to the Jordan River.
Yeah, and he's up to his neck in the water.
up to a 40-day period, during that the water stops and notice sort of all of the elements
of creation, not just the living creatures of the water but the water itself, signifying
the angels, the spiritual, the spirits associated with them are all praying and interceding
on his behalf as he repents, right?
And praying for his forgiveness.
Yeah.
And note, this might be familiar to folks from somewhere,
the New Testament, that literally directly talks about
the devil transforming himself into an angel of light.
Yeah, to trick Eve the second time.
So that's some groundwork laid for us to build upon now.
Alright, well
That wraps up the first half of this episode of The Laura's Spirits.
We'll be right back in a moment.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, this is John Maddocks. I know you thought I retired.
But as Michael Corleone and the Godfather said,
Just what I thought I was out.
They pulled me back in.
Seriously though, I am both honored and excited
to begin producing a series of audio documentaries
as special editions of Father Tom Soroka's popular live show,
Ancient Faith Today.
These documentaries will be designed to explore in some depth
various topics of interest to Orthodox Christians.
Topics, uh...
as the reception of converts into the Orthodox Church, a humanism, an Orthodox look at the
environment, deaconesses, and many more.
The intent of the forebath is to give various views, ample opportunity to express their
opinions in a non-debate and ironic setting.
They will all be pre-recorded and produced, and then played on ancient faith today,
time allotted afterward for comments and reactions.
Viacall
emails and texts. I hope you'll tune in.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody. We're talking fiatphony and we just did a whole bunch of
stuff about bail and...
Adam, Adam up to his neck in the river Jordan.
So yeah, we're on our way.
That's a fun stuff.
So yeah, well, why don't we talk about the actual feast itself.
Obviously people listen to the first half.
They caught some stuff.
I'm sure I don't, I don't know.
Normally we wait to the third half.
It's true.
But we like to mix it up once in a while.
A lot of people to be a little surprised.
Yeah, we can, we can change format.
a few people. There's going to be those people. It's like the people who try to show up,
like just for the gospel reading, right? Like they're going to, you're going to tune in
it like eight, 10. We've had darn it. They already covered the topic. We've had, well,
we've had people that they're like, well, can I just listen to the bits that you guys
do at the end? And I'm like, well, you can, but it's kind of all predicated upon the three
hours that came before I'd but sure look man I love eating
the bird ends, but you don't eat just the bird ends, right?
Like you got to get a slice of the good meat too.
Yeah.
Get yourself a slice of the brisket, ladies and gentlemen.
That's what life's all about.
I'm a pulled pork guy actually since I spent so many years in North Carolina.
So yeah, with you know, wouldn't turn down brisket.
Then I do like, but I have room in my stomach for all God's barbecues.
That is for sure.
Okay.
but you know, pulled port
with vinegar and maybe some hot pepper, that's the top of the heap for me.
Yep, with Okra.
We will get into this here.
Hush puppies.
I've spent too much time in Texas.
That's fine.
I mean, I'll eat an experience.
It's fine.
So Ed, you know, I've discovered that you could put jalapenos in literally anything.
That does seem to be acting.
And you could deep fry literally anything, but although the greatest thing, greatest thing,
and then we'll get back to the topic because I know how many huge fans we have of my
digressions.
But the best was during the brief period where I was a guard in a Texas prison.
what this literally was a common occurrence. Like you cook up a pot of chili.
and we'd spray our pepper spray into it for seasoning.
We as people don't know this, but pepper spray, even the sort of variety that civilians
can't buy is just pure capsicum.
It's just pepper.
There's no additives.
So you mix it into the pot, spicy chili.
It's all good.
So yeah, now back to theophony.
I don't have a good segue for that even.
So the outfit like guys.
spicy chili, pot, the holy water baptism that it seems like there should be something, but there isn't.
So as we alluded to way back at the beginning, the theophany is probably, and you know,
how do you number this? We're going to go ahead and say it's the second oldest Christian feast.
Yeah, okay, oldest oldest being posca
Well, sort of, specifically Christian. Right. Right. Not a Christian transformation of a Jewish
feast. Right. Which Paska and Pettacost directly are. Right. Paska is the Greek word for Passover.
Passover. Yeah. Right. So and not to go back to that earlier rant, but I really wish we'd translated
it in English. The hymns would make so much more sense if we were talking about a new and glorious
pass over.
Rather.
than a new eglory is Posca.
Because what's the old and less glorious Posca?
Yeah, exactly.
So that's, you know, Posca is Passover.
We're celebrating it differently in Christ, but it's still Passover.
And Pentecost is still, Pentecost, we're celebrating it differently in terms of the new covenant,
instead of the old covenant.
in terms of sort of new Christian faiths.
the offede is the second oldest because we know it was around from at least
to the very early part of the second century AD. So the early 100s, we know
the offede was being celebrated, but before that was actually St.
Stevens' Day. How about that? Which was the first martyr's feast. So I'll just
Go ahead and say this.
now. So if you want the game winning argument against your annoying internet friend who thinks
Christmas was a pagan holiday, you need to point out to him that like 250 300 years before
Christians were celebrating Christmas on December 25th, they already had feasts on December 27th
that are January 6.
So they didn't.
not need a new Winter Feast to replace anything. They already had Winter Feasts.
The fact say, see, this day is on Juvenileia.
So if they're just trying to replace Roman Feasts, that was already done.
No need to introduce Christmas. Done, make it, he says, stop it with that nonsense.
So from the very earliest evidence we...
have, theophany was celebrated as the feast of the incarnation. Right? We tend now, again
to look at the feast of the Nativity, Christmas, or Jesus is born as being the primary site
of the incarnation. Let me argue that even for the perspective of Christian doctrine, that
does it make sense?
If you want to go for the perspective of Christian doctrine, the feast of the incarnation would actually be March 25th. Yeah, the annunciation. Not concept.
25th the conception of the Lord. Right. Yeah.
But but this is sort of the feast of the incarnation and and what we mean by that is what we're going to be exploring for the rest of the episode.
Right. Because we'll start with what we don't mean by that.
Right. And I don't care. I'm just gonna say stuff. So so as you as you might expect.
I think that a very dumb surface level reading of that.
fact led 18th and 19th century scholars to some really bad conclusions based on bad
presuppositions.
Right.
So what do I mean by that?
So we have to remember some of the presuppositions we're dealing with, what we're dealing with
18th and 19th century scholarship.
And this isn't just biblical scholarship.
Now we're getting a historical scholarship at church history and Von Harnack and this
kind of stuff.
you
What are our presuppositions?
We have a presupposition.
Everything starts simple and then gradually gets more complex.
This sort of evolutionary hypothesis for everything.
So that's one assumption.
And it's an assumption because it's not provable.
It's a first principle.
It's just a presupposition that that's the way things work.
One could just as well take the opposite assumption.
thing start out very calm.
complex and nuanced and then get watered down. Right? Like I could argue that just as easily.
It gives you just as many examples, right? But this is the presupposition. Things start
simple over time they get more complex, elaborate, right? And put into place, right? So there's
an assumption. That means when we're talking about church history that...
whatever we have with the apostles and the quote unquote historical Jesus.
Very simple.
Right.
Very so they're starting over, starting a new religion.
It's very simple, very basic.
Just a bunch of hippies who are like, Hey man, just love everybody.
Be cool.
Like don't own stuff, right?
Like that's early Christianity, right?
And then, you know, all of a sudden all these bishops and stuff show up out of nowhere.
And ruin everything.
Really fast too.
It's kind of amazing.
But um...
So it starts this real simple and the complexity comes later.
The other major presupposition comes out of 16th, 17th century, this idea of a taxonomy
of religions.
We've talked about this before that human religion as a whole, as a human construct, starts
out simple and then gets work complex, gets refined, improves.
And so this is where you can construct the chart.
that begins with some kind of animism among cavemen and then ends with 19th century German Lutheranism.
Right, the culmination of all human religion. Right, so, and I say that fluently, but I could
put you to books that argue that seriously. So this kind of thing, and have these, you know,
whether it's polytheism and then there's monotheism and monotheism is more sophisticated, it develops
out of polydism.
And so, presupposition is all the apostles, all of the early Christians of the first
century AD are unitarian monotheists.
They think there's only one God that exists and that only one God is one person, right?
So then, right?
Obviously, all of these folks, and again, you can just read the books, I'll reject the
idea that there's any idea of the Trinity in the first century.
Right.
Because that would be crazy to Jewish people.
Now we know that's not true, right?
At least the people around this show know that's the opposite of true, right?
But again, these are the presuppositions.
And so when it comes to Christ, right, like the disciples, all just that Christ was this
cool guy, kind of a prophet who they hung out with who taught them all to love everybody
and not own stuff.
And uh...
You know, he died, but they thought like his spirit lived on in them and stuff, right?
Totally awesome
And then you have to go through these evolutionary stages to get from that to thinking that Jesus is God
Yeah
Right and so a
Whole evolutionary process of Christology gets constructed FC Bowers the big guy
Bye.
this, right? Where you start out with what's called a low Christology. Jesus is just a human guy. He's a
prophet in some sense, right? Charismatic spiritual leader. However they define that, the historical Jesus.
And then they start to think, oh, well, no, like he was more than that, right? And then he kind of
gets promoted and promoted until, oh, now at Nicae, we're going to say he's God, right? And again,
See our whole series.
about the Son of Man, Old Testament stuff, right?
About how all that's punk-um, right?
But now, if you have that idea, that construct, right?
Which I will give him credit for.
Friend of the show, Barterman, used to have
and now doesn't for the record.
He famously wrote a book called,
How Jesus Became God that was just laying out that.
Yeah.
It a very...
NPR friendly way, but he's now sort of repudiated that he now has a different view.
He has a version of the early high crystallogy view.
Hey, there might be hope for him yet.
Well, I know I still don't think he's right, but he's much closer than he was.
Yeah.
He's rejected a lot of that nonsense.
Mark's call in.
Yeah, it's like the show barter, but it is always welcome to call it and discuss anything he wants.
Um, but uh, if you take that pair,
paradigm, and then you drop in the fact that, oh, look, at the beginning of the second
century, Christians are celebrating the baptism of Christ in the Jordan by St. John the
Forerunner, St. John the Baptist as the feast of the incarnation.
What do you do with that?
Well, what you do with that is, oh, they thought that when
he was baptized in the Holy Spirit, descended upon him, that's when he became the Messiah,
or that's when he became divine.
This must be one of the steps.
That's called an adoptionist Christology.
Christ is at the begotten son of the Father.
He's the adopted son of the Father.
This is the moment of that adoption.
Today, you are my son, today I have begottenly.
Taking that very literally, as if it wasn't a quote from a Psalm used at the coronation
of a King of Israel.
anyone.
So that all gets fed into that paradigm.
Here's why that's dumb.
See here's part of the problem here, right?
Is that you start with presuppositions,
you filter data like of this historical data
about the piece of the offene,
through those presuppositions.
You come to a conclusion,
but there needs to be this other step
where you look at the conclusion
and you look at all of the other historians.
data. And see if your conclusion makes sense. Not if like your mode of reasoning that got you from point A to point B makes sense.
But does point B make sense with reality and the rest of the data? Those are two different things, right? And so even though you can see that logic, right?
The
The second question is possibly the most important one, right?
What do I mean by that? By this conclusion, ultimately being dumb.
Well, there are a whole bunch of groups that did have adoption as
Christologies in the second century. Yeah.
Totally. And then a bunch of other Gnostic groups, right?
And they all got condemned.
They didn't get condemned later. It's all like at the Council of
And I see that they were like, oh, crud, we need to go back and condemn all these guys.
because now we've got this new teaching that he's God.
They were condemned at the time.
They were condemned concurrently.
They were condemned at the beginning of the second century
by mainstream Christians, right?
So how could mainstream Christianity be liturgically
celebrating something that they were simultaneously
condemning his heresy among certain sects?
That doesn't make any sense.
That's the problem with trying to analyze bits of this
in isolation from all the rest.
Right.
So it's not about, is there a flaw in your argument from A to B?
It's does B make sense?
Yeah.
Right.
Does B make sense with the rest of the facts of the rest of reality?
And I have to say,
well, I don't have to, but I'm good to say.
I can feel it.
Even a lot of
even a lot of
Orthodox sources respected and respectable Orthodox sources on anti-dice
Christianity get this wrong.
And again, and I'm not I'm not saying this to go ahead. I was gonna say yeah
some kind of suggests like okay this is the reality Christ is truly God he's
truly man, but over time they sort of realize that.
right. That's that's how they kind of get this wrong. Right. So so I will use
an example because I'm using him as an example because he is the best example
not because he's the worst example. Right. And that's Father John Bear. I'm not
going after Father John Bear. I'm not seeking revenge just because the last time
he and I spoke he made fun of me about my wedding registry. But that's another
story.
Um, I have to add this to the James old Jones story.
Yeah, that's a point.
But the way that I see it, very well written book, right?
And he does the best version of this.
He does the Orthodox version of this,
but it's still a version of this is the problem, right?
So his book, like I said, I'm using that as the best example,
but there are lots of other Orthodox books
and non-Orthodox books about that early part
of church history and patristics
that are doing the same.
mostly from the 20th century, late 20th century.
Just accept sort of the academic narrative
about the development of doctrine as a fact.
Like these are just the facts we have to work with.
This is data, right?
Yeah.
And so, okay, as an orthodox priest, as an orthodox scholar,
I want to come at this data from an orthodox perspective.
So the nice thing doctor of the Trinity is true.
it got discovered over time, right?
It unfolded over time in the understanding of the church,
et cetera, et cetera, right?
So I'm not saying it's flawed,
isn't it's wrong or bad or harmful to read or anything?
I'm saying it's wrong in the sense of just those things
that were presumed to be data are not data.
They're bad conclusions based on bad presuppositions.
And we can we can
reject that whole thing and we've been doing that on this show right we've laid out the positive case
again in the episode about the Son of Man and the angel of the Lord and those things
that Christology there's not really a discontinuity between Judy second-table Judaism and early
Christianity on Christology not much a one right so I'm not saying that to say Father John's book
He has a lot of books I really like.
Even that one.
is a really well written book. I'm just saying it's now kind of out of date.
Because we've been able to discard some of those bad conclusions. We don't have to try to work
around them and frame them. We could just jettison them. And let me also say, I hope that every book
I write eventually becomes outdated. My hope is that, you know, a hundred years from now,
Now somebody you'll, you know.
look at a copy of religious apostles and be like,
and it's not really worth reading anymore
because he doesn't know about the second set of Dead Sea Scrolls.
Right? I hope that happens.
I hope that like human knowledge and our understanding of the faith
and of our tradition continues to increase. Right?
I want to help with that with my own writing,
but I'm trying to help with that like in real time.
So hopefully by the time I've been gone a few decades,
everybody will have moved on and understand everything better
than I ever did. Right? That's my hope.
So that's not a shot at Father John anyway. I know there's someone furiously typing on
the internet. Oh, we got stars. Emails are being sent. But yeah. But if Father John wasn't
called me and talk about it, I'd be happy to just talk with you. It's better.
Did you hear what they said? Yeah, but I'm totally happy to talk with them about that.
And we probably end up talking about a whole bunch of other stuff unrelated to that. But
So it's important that we don't fall back into that.
Right.
So that's a negative statement about what we don't mean when we say that the
offety is the feast of the incarnation. We don't mean that Christ's baptism is the
point at which he was incarnate. That's the takeoff point of our Christology.
That that's when he becomes the Messiah. That that's when he becomes the Son of God,
et cetera, et cetera. None of those things are things that we're saying. Right? Yeah.
Yep. Yep. So now we're going to come from a few different angles of what we are saying.
Right.
And we just won one note before we move on to that.
Did they still play the disclaimer before the show?
I don't know.
I didn't, you know, I didn't hear it play when we were...
They're probably gonna want to bring that back.
Let me just say, okay.
So but now moving on.
Oh man.
Thanks.
Hey, that disclaimer's doing some of your work for you.
Right?
The email you had father Andrew at AXHA.
Sure.
So, what are some things that are happening?
So, we've talked before on the show about how within the Old Testament, within the Hebrew Bible,
language that was traditionally applied within Bale worship to Bale is applied instead Yahweh the God of Israel.
and some of the big examples of that are Psalm 104 or 103.
It talks about God walking on the wings of the wind and Leviathan, who he made to sport,
meaning to play with like a pet, right?
In the waves, this is sort of taking that bail language.
And you can see with Leviathan, it's not now, oh, your big epic battle was against my house cat, right?
This is a reappropriation, right?
Again, unlike some of those fine scholars of the 19th, it...
really 20th century. This is not the smoking gun that Yahweh is really bail under another
name. There's something deliberate going on here, right? Saying, no, this is Yahweh
not bail. Daniel 7 of course has the son of man coming on the clouds of heaven. These
are just a few quick examples that we've gone over in more detail in the past. Job 41
talks about Leviathan.
There's a there.
That's the passage and show where there's kind of a chaos comp,
view of creation, go back and listen to past episodes if you don't know what chaos
comp is, other than a cool sounding German word.
And Isaiah 27 verse 1 also talks about Leviathan, right?
So this is, this language is taken.
This is a sort of direct action to say, no, your stories about bail are wrong.
You're giving glory to bail that belongs actually to Yahweh.
who created everything, including Bale and through Bale out of heaven, etc., etc.
out of the heavens. But what we see in the Feast of Fiafini, in the iconography,
in the liturgics, is that that same language, and that same imagery, same symbol,
is taken and applied to the incarnate.
Christ. Right? There are a lot of examples of this. Right? In the icon of the
offeney, one thing that might jump out is that Yaman Nahar are hanging out in the
Jordan River, that at the bottom, the little dudes. Yeah. The Greek inscription
that's a Thelassie and Putnamos, right? That's C and River. That's Yaman,
or often Yodhavani actually often see that now.
Yeah.
He's the little dude riding on the yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So here, and you see the trampling on the snakes or the serpents or the dragons right like Leviathan.
The fugitive serpent.
So this imagery that's typically applied to bail is now being applied.
Not only to Yahweh the God of Israel, but to the incarnate Christ.
Right. So, and it's being done, it's being reapplied in this same kind of way. Right.
The same kind of way. So, there is this parallel being made between, on the one hand, you have this contest of Yau Avers' bail, both in him casting bail.
Bell that
devil into the underworld, right? The later conflicts we described. On the other side, you have
Adam versus Bale or Adam versus the devil in Genesis 3, right? So in terms of battles between
Yahweh and Bale, he's about, I don't know if we just take the ones recorded in scripture 27 and
know, right? But
Adam and his descendants are like the opposite, like O and a million, right?
In terms of the devil.
But so we have here not just because this is the incarnate Christ,
not just victory, um,
13th victory for Yahweh, but the first victory for Adam.
Yeah, and this is...
Let us see.
You know, this is why, as we said, you've got those little critters down there in the water
in many cases and Theopani icons, not all of them, but a lot of them.
So it's not just Bale, right?
It's not just Yamuna Har.
It's also the sense of Christ cleansing the creation from demonic power entirely.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, that's what we, I was going to say we had someone call it.
And that was their question.
I was like, I told Trudy to tell him,
we're about to do that.
It's coming.
People tracking with us.
Right.
And so we've talked about this in terms of Christ divine identity before.
Yeah.
Right.
That part of Christ divine identity, right?
In the Torah, if you touch something that is unclean, you become unclean.
Right.
And Christ touches.
something that is unclean it becomes clean. So he touches a leper, right? The
leper becomes whole is healed. He touches a dead body that is unclean, the dead
body comes back to life. Yeah. Right. And this is part of as we've talked about
the manifestation of his divine identity. Right. But so it's key here. What we
really want to key in on here in this episode is that the offeneer, the piece of
the incarnation.
also involves here Christ's human identity.
Right. His human identity in having this victory over bail over the devil.
Right. Over the powers.
This isn't just again round whatever that Yahweh wins.
This is the first round that humanity wins.
Yeah, it's a huge turning point for humanity.
That Adam wins. Right.
And the connection, shall we say, between St. John the Forerunner and Elijah that we talked
about in our episode about the Forerunner is fully at play here in the baptism.
We often, that element of Elijah gets kind of sideline here in this scene because there's
so much to talk about, right?
There's 87 different directions you can come at this, right?
And points you can make.
But it is fully in play here.
And not just in the spiritual, again, before we've talked about primarily spiritual sense,
right?
Sort of Elijah is the patron, the guide, the friend of St John the Four Runner, right?
But also, this is all intertwined, right?
So think about the situation of Judea at the time that...
is happening. Think about Herod. Herod who's been rebuilding the temple, the Sadducee families who
have the high priesthood and who are in charge of the temple and are corrupt. And wicked and Heretics
and everything else. Herod this evil, foreign king, who St. John is there opposing in the way a
Elijah
had to oppose AAB over and over and over and over again. And note, in this case, too,
involves his wife, who shouldn't be his wife. Right? Yeah, yeah, yeah. And it's kind of
his wife who's calling the shots. Let's cause in the problem. Right? And think about, right?
We... So, one of the Old Testament readings, we already mentioned this in passing, but
one of the Old Testament readings.
that we read in the great blessing of the water in the Vespro
Litergy for the offene is the story of the showdown amount
caramel with the bail.
Yeah, and it's not.
I know some people's and I have been guilty years ago, but I
got better of saying, you know, look, they just took every
reference to water in the old.
Right. Yeah.
And you got me to the water.
Yeah.
Yeah. That ain't it.
Right.
Yeah.
Um, this is about a showdown.
the story was showed out with bail and now we're having another showdown with bail.
But within that showdown with bail, right? Notice what is what is Elijah do, the proper
Elijah do? He soaks down the altar with water and then fire from heaven comes down upon
it. Yeah. Yeah. Which I ruined everybody's Sunday school by pointing out was lightning.
But, right, but then fire comes from heaven.
Right? But look at the language that St. John uses regarding baptism and regarding himself
in Christ. He baptizes with water when it's coming who's going to baptize with fire in
the Holy Spirit. Water, then fire, right? Fire from heaven. And that water and fire and
baptism language doesn't actually just get dumped after the story of
I mean, we hear that language on a feast of the four under where we're reading St. John saying that stuff.
Sure.
And the first few chapters of Luke, right, the beginning of Matthew, mainly.
But that doesn't just get forgotten.
Right?
Yeah, it gets brought up again, even though we kind of gloss over it later in Luke.
St. Luke's Gospel, for example.
for example. Yeah, in Luke chapter 12 verses 49 and 50, Christ says,
I came to cast fire on the earth and wood that it were already kindled.
I have a baptism to be baptized with and how great is my distress until it is accomplished.
Is that anybody's life verse?
Somebody somebody do the cross stitch and put lightning in it just for me.
Anyway, um, yeah.
And so this is...
This is this showdown language, right? We're not just reading it there for no reason
we're each because it's being alluded to in the story
Right over to go to the this is part of what this is the showdown with bail with the devil, right?
It's happening again. It's happening in Christ's baptism which is something we usually don't associate it with right
um and
and think about right
At that showdown
Be safe.
before it begins, Elijah, in the original Hebrew,
the way the question reads is essentially,
he says to the Israelites,
how long will you hover between two opinions?
And the language of hover there,
it's sort of the language of like a bird coming in
for a landing and like you've got two spots you can land
and you're kind of hovering in between
like you're trying to decide where to land, right?
And then I said, hey, if, if...
is God worship him, if you always got worship him, right? And this is exactly what St. John is
posing to the people who are coming out to him in the desert, right? Even to the point that when
some of the bad guys start to come out there, right, the people who he's been opposing, he says,
you brute of vipers who warned you to flee from the wrath to come.
Right?
Um.
And then comes that this actually may be, maybe by life first, because it's you
Brutavipers who weren't, you defle from the wrath to come.
And with such words and others, he proclaimed to them the good news.
Right.
That's right.
Good news.
They are for runner.
So, um, because that's great news, right?
You're a Brutavipers.
and you know, darn it, somebody words you. I was hoping.
But it's a good news everybody.
Right, but this is the same thing that he's posing
right to them.
And then the baptism of Christ is this critical moment
after which those who would come to follow
say John become followers of Christ.
Like my patron saint.
Yeah, Saint Andrew.
So,
and you know we call it
from Luke 12, right, in the context of that ministry, right, that ministry of Christ in his
sending out the 70s, sending out the disciples, ministering, you know, this counteroffensive
against the powers that be the king of the prince in Judea, we find out who loses, right,
we get told who loses, right, Satan, Christy's fall like lightning. There's my lightning,
Bye.
falls like fire from heaven, right? This contest he loses. So the one other element
that we should mention before we end this the second half is because I got
explicitly asked about it and I do almost every year by somebody in my parish.
They're listening to the hemnography and they hear all this language about the
Jordan River stopping and turning back and parting.
And we already saw a little of that actually in the life of Adam and Eve, but that comes
from the same place.
These are not literal references to say that this happened at Christ's baptism, right?
Like, Saint John and his gospel says Christ came up out of the water.
It's not that he tried to get baptized in the water part of it and he didn't get wet,
right?
So that, that hemographic language is at literal in that way, but it's alluding back
to someone else named Josh.
Joshua. Joshua, he led the people into the land of Canaan through the Jordan River when
the Jordan River parted in front of him.
This is about how Joshua of the Old Testament is a type of Jesus who of course has the same
name. And so again, what does that mean? Jesus is doing with these followers who come
to follow them, he's mounting a counteroffensive.
reconquista as it is as it were of the of Judea of Canaan right that is coming
to this again so this is this is language of this conflict this battle with the devil
that he is going to lose but it's a battle right again this is what we're really going to focus
on in the third half terms of the incarnation it's a battle that he is winning not only as another
victory.
of Yahweh over the devil over Baal, but as the first victory of humanity over the enemy.
Yeah. All right, well that's the second half, but there's a third half coming. So we will be
right back after our second and final break. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
psychology. And angels are often reducible to the better angels of our nature,
that is to our better human impulses and virtues. Talk of spirits is really about
psychology. But to the ancient mind of millennia ago, even up to the pre-modern mind of just centuries ago,
these are real beings with personal presence who inhabit our world and affect us.
Father Andrew provides a distillation and ex
of the material in the popular podcast, The Lord of Spirit,
which he co-hosts with Father Stephen DeYoung.
Get this brand new book today at store.AncientFaith.com.
That's store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with The Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's it.
555 AF radio.
And hey, you can get there's Kindle versions.
There's, you know, e-book.
There's an audio book.
You can listen to me read it to you.
Uh, I think somebody's got to talk to John Maddox.
Oh, this is the second time he's been inserted into this show.
He just doesn't want to retire.
Does he just want to come on Lord of Spirits?
Like this is, this is like turning into a whole Lucio ball begging Ricky to be in the
show.
thing. What should he be our first and only? No, we did for
but we don't have guests. We don't do guests. Right. Like if he
wants to call in, he could call in. Right. Right.
He's got every white friend of the show, Barterman privileges. But
I mean, he can still call in. We'd love to talk to you.
Is it just loneliness? Are you bored in your retirement? Right?
You could call a talk to us. We'll talk to you. We like you.
Allah
He's great actually John's great guy.
Well, don't give him a big head.
Come on.
He's fine.
I mean, yeah, he's solid.
Yeah.
So yeah, we're talking, we're talking the
offony.
And again, this is not the baptism
episode that was another episode.
This is not the great blessing of water
episode. That was another episode.
Although, of course, those were closely related to this.
This is about the actual...
will feast itself, the event in the Jordan. Yeah, yeah, good stuff. And we're, you know,
if you're listening to this live, especially if you're on the new calendar, we're in the
Theophony Post-Festal period. It's going to be lasting for a few more days. So if you're
on the calendar, we're prepping yet. Yeah, yeah. From the old calendar, it's just what,
a week and a half or so away something like that. Yeah, so eight days. No eight days. Yes.
a week in a day. So yes, all right. So, you know, million dollar question in that great
hymn from Holy Week that we hear both on Holy Thursday night and then Holy Friday morning,
you know, the hymn that begins, he is suspended on the tree who suspended the earth over
the waters. One of the things it said is in there is he receives smidings or he's slapped
in the face, depending on which translation you're reading.
He who freed Adam and the Jordan.
So how does he?
How does he free Adam and the Jordan?
Like how what is what is what happens in the Jordan?
How is that about Adam being being saved?
Right. So I'm assuming you misspoke because the million dollar question would mean that
when I answer this, you give me a million dollars.
Oh, well, I'll write you a check.
So bother.
I mean, I can't guarantee what it'll do when you try to, you know,
Yeah, positive exact.
I can. But so right. So and it's not that that possible. Him is a great example. But there are a bunch
of other places. Oh, yes. Yes. Yeah. Leading up to in the Theophony liturgics, the hymns,
in the post Theophony period season that talk about Christ saving Adam, right? In some sense,
Right.
sometimes with the word save, right, as the verb other times with other similar verbs, but this idea that
at the ofteny, at this event of Christ's baptism, right, Adam is saved. And we've already
kind of alluded to where we're going with this, right? That's what we've sort of built up to
in the second half is that we're going as that Christ
incarnate wins this victory over Adam's
and extended me the devil, right?
But to really sort of understand the fullness of what this means, we need to talk a little
more about the incarnation.
And some of this, a fair amount of this is sort of bug squashing.
It's sort of, we have some kind of bad ideas or bad habits of thought about this, right,
that needed a kind of squish.
to help us understand.
So, we want to be clear right off the bat.
We already kind of said this about the question
about angels repenting, right?
We're not talking about mechanisms here.
We're not going to explain to you
how the incarnation works.
Yeah.
Okay.
I think it's important to remember everybody.
It is God who saves, right?
That's how it works.
God saves.
Yes, yeah.
So yeah, or the other good answer to how it works if you want to go with the himnography the churches
Inephabilly there you go
Inephabilly is a beautiful word because it effable means unable to be described in words
Just kind of ironic because there's a word for it. But anyway, I'm at a loss for words. He says in words. Yes
But yeah, so yes the incarnation happens in Ephabilly. That's how it works
But...
We're approaching this from, as we've said many times before, what the incarnation does
in the sense of what the incarnation accomplishes.
What it's ongoing meaning is in various regards.
And again, this is not exhaustive.
No episode of this show ever is exhaustive.
You may have noticed this if you've listened to many episodes.
Exhausting.
Right.
Exhausting definitely.
Yeah.
Definitely not for me. I'm perpetually reinvigorated but
Once a list of other in exotheranjus up passes bedtime
But they're not exhaustive right we come back to these things
We already did an episode of the great blessing of waters at the offene and here we are again, right?
So
Trust me there's no claim here that we're now going to give you a thorough
Explication of the incarnation.
of Christ. There is no such thing. No. Right. Even from the perspective of meaning and what it
accomplishes, there's no completely comprehensive description. Right. We could keep this show running
for another 25 years. Do every episode on this topic and not get done. Okay. If we were trying to
be exhaustive, but that would be exhausting. So we're not going to do that. Except for you or
perpetually reinvigorated. Yes, yes. Well, I could, but I'm not going.
to. I just don't want to. So where do we start with the incarnation? Well, in terms of defining
it, in terms of the language that the tradition, the Christian tradition has given to us.
This is really the Christian tradition. This is third acumenical council stuff, right?
the third ecumenical council which John Calvin
least claimed in writing he disagreed with none of. That's highly debatable. But, right. So,
third-eccupatical council, condemnation of historian is a first-christological council.
This is universal Christian stuff, right? Or at least it used to be the good old days before people
could just identify as Christian and believe all kinds of crazy things. But I choose to live in the
the world of the past.
Um, that language that we have about the incarnation is that Christ is a divine person.
Right. One of the three divine persons, one of the three persons who shares in the divine nature. Right. The father of the son, the Holy Spirit.
Christ is one of them. He is the son.
Who takes upon himself human nature.
That is the language.
Yeah. Right.
I'm there's there's other language.
Yes.
well, like there's like St. Max miss talks about him being a composite person.
Right. And there's the what we could go to just go to Calcede and then there's other
language, right? Yes. Yes. Exactly. Yeah. 100 years later. But this is 120 years later.
This is where we're starting. Right. Yeah. Um, crisis divine person takes upon himself human
nature, right? But even that, even this language, right, is now.
greatly misunderstood. Right. And part of that, as we've talked about many times before
on the show, one of the perils of the English language Latin has the same problem is that
English tends to rayify things. Yeah, meaning that turn things into things. Yeah, when we see
the word nature, we think that like nature is a thing like a like somebody who will say he took
on a human nature.
Because if that's a thing, that's an isolatable, describable thing that exists in time and
space, a human nature.
Right.
Even sometimes I'll hear people, not super informed people, but I'll hear people say,
well, you know, an icon of Christ is just a depiction of his human nature.
Right.
Which is fascinating to me because if someone told me dry
a human nature. I don't know what I would draw. Yeah. Right? Like I could draw a human
person. But I don't know how I would draw a human nature. That's because a human nature.
It's not a thing. Um, yeah. And, and the language I used was very deliberate about Christ
being a divine person, meaning he's one of the three persons who share in the divine
nature. A nature is something that is shared among
Hi, possesses among persons among individual existence, right? So all the dogs in the world share the canine nature
Right a dog is not a creature that has like a canine nature attached to it in some way
Right and I could I could draw a bad. I have no artistic talent
But I could draw a bad picture of one of my
heathen dogs, but I could not draw a picture of its canine nature, right? Does that's not a thing,
right? So human natures were shared by all humans. The sharing, by the way, is what
consubstantial means. It's what homo-usios means. That's the language from Calceden.
That Christ, according to divine nature, is homo-usios with the Father and the Spirit.
And according to his human nature, his homo-usios with all of us.
Yeah, yeah, all eight billion of us right now plus all the ones who came before
So
That nature is what is shared right and
We've talked about this before
But as a reminder the way that the the the Greek term nature fees is not a biblical term
It really is it starts to show up in the New Testament in St. Paul in particular
But he and I'm not going to go into this right now, but he repurp-
He uses it in a very different way than it was commonly used in Greek before that.
It's not in the Greek Old Testament tradition.
And but Fisi's comes to be used in Christian theology the way body was used previously in sort of
Semitic thought. This is... and so remember our definition of body on the show.
So it's a nexus of potentialities and powers, right?
So when we say, right, Christ is a divine person, right?
We mean he is a person who possesses all of the things that it means to be God.
Yes, right? All the powers, all the things, whatever we want to talk about, attributes, whatever language we want to use,
When we're talking about the Father, Christ has the same thing.
Right? That's what we mean. Bye.
him sharing in the divine nature and him taking upon himself our human nature then means
he adds to that, adds human powers and potentialities.
So now he can sleep.
Right.
He can do all those things that humans do.
And now he can voluntarily grow hungry, right, and tired and all of this.
and the third ecumenical council has, I mean there's a big pile of language.
related to this. I can really driven home if you read the actual texts, but there's one that's
sort of half a sentence that expresses this in a pretty compact way. And it says, for the
scripture has not said that the word united to himself the person of man, but that he was made flesh,
made flesh. Right? Sometimes straight out of John 1.
and of course lots of stuff in St. Paul as well.
But again, the idea that he's made flesh,
meaning that he now has our human abilities.
He is what it means to be human as well.
Right. So there is not this sort of human person Jesus,
the man Jesus, right, or whatever, who I say.
and then the logos or God the Sun.
or the Son of God, or however we want to describe it,
as these two sort of separate entities,
right, not even separatable in speech, right?
But the one divine person takes upon himself,
these human potentially, voluntarily,
these human potentialities and powers,
which are added, right?
That added is also very important, right?
And not understanding this has led to some really horrible and destructive theology at the fringes of Protestantism.
This isn't mainstream Protestant stuff. This is...
This is...
Fringe Protestant stuff.
Look at it, you Bethel. Why'd you name yourself after what are the places where there was a golden calf?
Anyway.
Fringe and cringe.
It ended up being appropriate.
Um, wow.
Right in that the way it's talked about a lot and and and in really extreme ways in those circles, but in less extreme ways in a lot of other circles
is the idea that
rather than seeing Christ continuing to be God in the full and complete sense in the incarnation but taking upon himself also human potentialities powers
that taking on the becoming
human taking on those human aspects somehow meant he had to give up some aspects of his divinity.
Yeah, when they see that or put them on hold or whatever. Yeah, he said it aside. Yeah, like,
and this is theoretically based on the language of him emptying himself. Right. Kanoos and so
they were sort of literalized that. Right. Like he emptied something out. Right. And
And if you read Philippians 2, the Carman Christie there, we've read it on the show.
in a past episode. But it's very clear what that self-emptying is talking about.
It's talking about Christ pouring himself out even unto death on the cross, his humiliation,
right, and humility and suffering and death. That's what that emptying is. It's not talking about him
stopping being God. And even if you can't see how catastrophic it is on the one side,
right? Meeting on the other side. Oh, well, he kind of put that stuff on.
to be human for a while, right? Even if you can't see how destructive and wrong that is on that side.
What does that mean on the other side?
What does that mean when Christ is sent into heaven?
Yeah, I mean, I've seen people say that he's not human anymore because he's got again now.
Then he leaves, you know, he transforms into human and then it kind of transforms back.
Yeah, because that's where it really becomes a problem.
Right.
It's not so much the divinity on hold that's this horrible heresy. That's wrong, but it's a destructive sort of heresy.
But the other half that Christ somehow ceases being human, right? In any sense, ceases being human.
I won't name anyone, but in any sense, ceases being a male human, this is rank heresy that destroys the gospel.
Yeah, yep, yep, right.
rank, he is rank referring to the smell.
Yeah, thank you.
William Lane Craig level.
Yeah.
Wow.
But fortunately not on all topics like William Lane.
I mean, you've got you've got the sin of Jeroboam sort of the bot and then you've got William Lane Craig.
Incident of William Lane Craig except his is just ubiquitous theological error.
Wow.
Being fracally wrong.
Um, right. So, Chris.
This doesn't give up anything.
And we have a prayer that we pray very frequently,
the spree of the Orthodox Church, about Christ, right?
The Christ in the grave with the body,
in the hands of the souls God, and paradise with the thief,
and the throne of the Father in the spirit of the South,
Christ filling all things, like self-uncertain scribed.
Right.
So at the incarnation, Christ does not leave
the throne of the Father, right?
Right.
When he rises from the dead, he doesn't leave
with the thief.
Right? I'll be back 40 days. See you. See you, Dismiss. Right? Yeah.
And he doesn't even, this is key to he rise from the dead. He doesn't leave Hades either.
But it's a whole other thing. It's another story. Read Ephesians. Anyway. So, right. And so
So...
What we're getting at here, this is another question.
I know this is a thing that makes people's wheels grind.
I don't know if it makes sense to explode,
but it makes wheels grind.
The way we've talked about Christ being sort of eternally
incarnate, right?
In a sense, right?
Part of the core of this, and we're going to be,
Here's a T
are post-past-showfast, we're going to be going deep into this in a series of episodes.
But part of this is how we view identity, the identity of a person, including this case,
the identity of Christ.
Right, but this extends to the identity of any given person.
And that's that we sometimes, only sometimes.
I'm going to unpack that.
So we tend to get this
So we tend to get this.
retrospectively. We look back on our life, right? And I think about based on my
memories or looking at old pictures, right? Me when I was seven, right? Nightmare
as child. I say, were you ever seven? Out of control. I was seven. I was not
small, but I was seven. And at a terror. But me and
set it right. I would say that's me.
at seven. Right, that's still me. Right, I am the same person
that is now. I'm not that's not a different person. Now, I
might say, I'm a different person now that I wasn't a pass
meeting, I have changed. Right. But it's still me that's
changed. Yeah. Right, like I wasn't literally like I didn't
go through a Star Trek transporter and get reput back
together, right? What I mean by that is
Yes, it's true. Every time someone uses a transporter and star trek, they die and are closed. It's a one
impossibility. Bones was right the whole time. So many hikers are there. Sorry. Yeah.
But so I'm not literally a different person. Right. So we kind of understand that retro
prospectively.
But we don't understand that prospectively.
And here's what I mean by that.
I don't know that we'd recognize
that the seven year old me was already me,
the me I am today.
Right?
Right.
Then when you talk about me,
my identity is not a snapshot.
Right?
or a series of snapshots.
in that my identity is sort of protean and shifts every second, right?
We've talked about how the matter in my body, yeah, every few years gets sloughed off and gets
replaced by a completely different matter, right? And that's why we talked about identity is not
a function of being composed of the same matter. Remember the boat of theses?
So, identity is not being...
the same material. Right? But identity is what carries through all of that. Right? And so
when we talk about who a person is, right, we're not talking about this snapshot of some particular
time in their life, but we're talking about the whole span of their life. Here's a place
where we understand this clearly.
Okay, when we talk about us.
St.
Okay, so we talk about St. Nicholas, right?
When we talk about St. Nicholas,
and we tell a story of the life of St. Nicholas,
we don't start it with like Nicholas was born,
and then there's at some point in his life where he achieves the status or transforms into St. Nicholas.
Right. Right. You know, it just say St. Nicholas.
Right. He's St. Nicholas, or start to finish,
the person St. Nicholas that whole story
is his identity, is who St. Nicholas is. Right? We're not just talking about any given snapshot.
An example, an opposite example, Tertullian, not a saint, right? Not a saint. Was it important
writer and theologian within the church for a chunk of his life. Right, and then ends up...
Joining the mountainous joins a heretical sect
Right, and that's where he ends his life right
We don't say well he was Saint Tertelian until he joined the mountainists
Right and then he stopped being holy
Right rather we talk about him in terms of his life as a whole his identity is his whole life
Right his whole life and
And that's why you have saints who are penitent, right?
When we talk about David in the Old Testament.
We're not just taking a snapshot because there's some pretty bad snapshots the whole best
Shiba thing right
But we're talking about his whole life
Right that's who the prophet and King David is right his whole life and so
The same is true of
Christ
We're talking about Christ. We're talking about Christ
Talking about his entire existence which means we're talking about his eternal existence
and his whole earthly life.
That's his identity, right?
So Ricky Bobby is incorrect
and Taladega Knights.
You cannot choose the baby Jesus as your favorite Jesus.
No, they did that for comedy,
but we're just coming out of the Christmas season.
I think a lot of people's favorite Jesus is the baby Jesus.
Yeah.
Right?
Baby Jesus doesn't tell you to do things you don't want to do.
He's just cute and you can come and adore him.
You get to take these slices, right?
These snapshots, right?
But at the same time, right, when his mother, St. Joseph, the Magi, the shepherds at different
times, by the way, were looking at the baby Jesus.
they were seeing Christ.
They were seeing the divine logos. They were seeing God. They were seeing Christ. They were seeing the one who's crucified
For the foundation of the world. They're seeing the one who's resurrected. They're seeing the one who's seated at the right hand of the Father
They're seeing him and all of that is his identity
right
so
Identity the identity of a person right like this is one
But for us...
as humans, right?
And we've talked about this before on the show.
And again, like I said, we're gonna go deep into this
in a series in a few weeks, in a couple months.
For us as humans, we sort of,
our identity, who we are, sort of unfolds
that has worked out in time and space,
because we experience reality
within the categories of time and space.
Right
So, for us, we sort of become who we are and come to understand who we are, right?
And this unfolds and we participate in it and come to understand it.
But we can't do that with Christ because Christ is God, right?
We don't understand how a bat experiences things.
Let alone how God experiences things, right?
So we don't know how God...
experiences his Godhood, right? Like I mean that's even that language is silly, right? In the sense that like what? Right? Like so
that that spiritual reality, right, is eternal. Christ is eternal, right?
And this way of describing it has to be true. Why does it have to be true?
For Hebrews to be true. Yeah, where it says
Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and today and forever
Right, it's not just today and forever
Yeah, it's also yesterday
Even if the yesterday that we're talking about is when he was 15 in Nazareth
Right
Or before his birth in
again.
Bethlehem or before his conception.
Right? All of those yesterdays he was the same as he is today and will be forever.
Right? That's what Hebrews is getting at.
And so because what once we start to get at and again,
Again, this is not something we can explain and comprehend and explain how it works.
This is something we can describe the outline of and sort of wonder at, right?
The incarnation.
It's ineffable.
But as we start to understand this, right, we could see how bad it is.
It destructive of our real understanding of who Christ is to try and
psychologist him, right?
To try to attribute, well, he must have had some separate human consciousness
like ours.
Right and try and say well since Jesus is man we can understand how he experience
How did he experience being God as a man?
He's not a man right it's taking our human nature right that doesn't work. We don't know what it's like to be God
right
So all of those kinds of things any any time you hear anyone interpreting anything in scripture or doing anything
The Bible is a very important thing,
that requires you, that requires
entering into the head of Jesus
and what Jesus knew.
when he knew it to those kind of things, run, don't walk, right? That's not going to go anywhere
good. And people will go there with no ill intent. No ill intent whatsoever. Completely well-meaning
people will wander off into those woods, but they're woods. They're dark scary woods and you just
say out of them. Right. And as we've talked about before, right, just as grace entry.
the waters purifies the waters, right? This victory, right? Christ's entry into our humanity purifies
our humanity. The humanity he shares with us, right? So this victory of his that's described
by the gospel isn't just an individual victory for him, not just even the victory of Yahweh anymore,
victory of God but it's also our victory.
right? And Christ shares the spoils of that victory that he's won with the rest of us.
Right? This is one of the fundamental building blocks to understanding salvation in the New Testament.
This idea of Christ winning this victory and then sharing with us in the spoils. Right?
And finally, right, Christ victory, where Adam failed, Adam ends up naked and then...
being clothed with the garments of skin. Right? In Christ, right? Our humanity is recloved
as St. Paul says in 1 Corinthians 15, with immortality, not with mortality, but with immortality
now, with the divine life and the divine glory that belonged to Christ. Right? And so this
metaphor of being recloed.
getting rid of the garments of skin and those being replaced by these new garments.
Right? It's a major sorry Calvinist thing. This is not about earned merits, earned
credit, good deeds, credit with God that earned salvation, whether earned by us or by Christ.
That's not in the picture. Right? We're clothed with who Christ is, right? With who
Christ is. As many of you as a
been baptized into Christ have put on Christ. Right? Not put on Christ deeds. Not put on
his honor, but put on Christ who he is. He became who we are so we could become who he is.
Right. And so this gives us again, I would say it's a full orbed picture. Again, not even
close to a comprehensive picture.
Right?
And outline.
of something that we can look at, right? Of what it means that in this moment, this moment,
which is really described as this showdown, this moment of battle, the beginning of this reconquest,
of the baptism of Christ, right? This is the victory then in Christ of humanity over our
ancient enemy and Adam gets saved in those waters.
Yeah.
For my final bit, I wanted to share one of the many hymns of theophony.
As I said at the beginning, I mean, there are Christian groups out there that don't have
theophony.
And I feel so bad.
I'm not, you know, like I'm really I'm not trying to be disdainful, but I just feel so
bad that some people don't get to do this.
I remember when I became Orthodox that the feast of theophony was just like...
a revelation to me. Certainly, you know, as a Christian, I had always believed that Jesus
was baptized, but I had no idea really what it was for, honestly. And then encountering
the Feast of Theophanie was just astonishing to me. And there are many, many, many, many
hymns connected with the Feast, but I just wanted to share one of them. And this comes
from the Vespers of Theophilus.
which in most years is going to be part of the Vespral Divine Litergy that is celebrated on the day before, so on the 5th of January.
In some years it's in great Vespras the night before, but in most years it's going to be the Divine Litergy on the day before the 5th.
So this is from towards the end of the the hymns that are connected with the
the psalm, Lord I have cried." And it says this,
When thou didst choose to save lost man,
thou dost not disdain to put on the likeness of a servant.
For it was meat for the O Lord God to accept what is ours for our sakes.
For when thou hast baptized in the flesh, O Redeemer,
thou dost make us worthy of forgiveness.
Therefore, we cry to the O Christ our benevolent God, glory to the Lord.
the and I mean in a lot of ways this hymn summarizes a lot of what we we were just
talking about especially a lot of the crystallological stuff but it's interesting
you know again this is this is the feast of the incarnation and this hymn
explicitly talks about the incarnation that Christ accepted what is ours human
nature for hour six. He did it.
for us. And when, and it takes says also he took on the form of a servant, you know, that he,
he humbled himself, right? But it also says that when he was baptized in the flesh, and it calls him
Oredemer, this is part of the, this is the redemption of human nature, Oredemer, it says that it's
make us worthy of forgiveness.
which is an interesting thing to say.
Some people might object to that, say,
why isn't everybody worthy of forgiveness?
And the answer is yes, everyone is worthy of forgiveness
because of what he did there.
But that doesn't mean it's a matter of like,
okay, we were valueless before, we were just trash.
But what it means is that we're now capable of receiving it.
Like it sort of opens the door.
Right?
We're counted. It's now fitting.
us to receive forgiveness. But it's not an automatic thing and it's not imposed on us.
Forgiveness is not imposed on mankind. The reception of it requires our cooperation.
Like the door is open, but we have to walk through it. Right. We have to participate
in it, you know, that what Christ does in the Jordan is for us.
For Adam, for all mankind, it's...
It's for us, but we can't receive it if we don't participate in it.
And participation number one is through baptism.
When we're baptized, we receive the blessing of the Jordan, the blessing that Christ gave,
the purification, the atonement, that Christ gave to the Jordan through baptism.
But we also received, speaking of this feast in particular, this blessing buys.
celebrating the feast. Right? And I mean, this is, like I said, this is my experience. I had never received the
blessing of the off and until I celebrated the feast. And if you haven't ever done it, then you, you
don't, not going to know what I'm talking about. So if that makes you feel sad, then you know, go do it.
go participate, right? And then also, like someone who lives into this, so it's not just a
about going and celebrating the feast day at church,
but also at home, there's things to do at home
that are related to this.
Get your house blessed, for instance, by the priest,
sing the hymns together at home,
especially like before meals and family prayer time and stuff.
But when you live into this,
when you are actually participating
and you're conforming your whole life to what Christ does
in the Jordan, then you become a theophanec person.
of course, yeah.
often means the appearing of God.
God is manifest in the flesh, in the server,
but then in you, in you.
And a theophonic person, then, is one who,
in whom God is manifest.
And it's not just a private personal experience.
That is an experience for the people around you as well.
When you live theophannically,
people will want to be baptized, will be baptized, right?
So theophonic mother in...
father, their children are baptized, but also their friends and their family are going
to be drawn into this as well if they're not already baptized. They're also going to be
drawn into the celebration of the feast. They're going to be drawn into all these things, because
we're all called, as we said, when we put on Christ in baptism, then others will approach.
And then they approach Christ. They're not approaching you. They're approaching Christ.
and approaching me, approaching me.
Christian Christ. So it's this moment of Christ's baptism in the Jordan, this moment of the
offene as this cosmic impact, right? And it participates in all of the great acts of
salvation that happen in the life of Christ, right? Like there's an image here also of his
harrowing of hideous. Like he stands in the waters, he stands in the abyss. He stands.
over the mouth of death, right?
But he's not swallowed up.
He defeats it all. He defeats the chaos.
He defeats the death. He defeats the destruction.
Right? There's so many things about the life of Christ.
You can see them sort of all nested in each other.
And that's just one example, right?
And we've talked about a few others.
So, yeah, that, you know, read the hymns.
If you miss the feast, if you're on the new calendar...
read the hymns. It still is in the immediate future if you're still celebrating according to the Julian calendar, so you can go and do that.
That'll be the 18th and 19th for those people.
So, but yeah, at least read the hymns.
They're just astonishing.
It's just magnificent. I just read you just one of them.
But there's so much more.
so much more so so powerful. Thanks be to God. Father Stephen your final thoughts.
So one of the things that comes with adolescence and my life is nothing if not
in extended adolescence is is a certain level of disgust with oneself.
It doesn't matter how happy it will.
you seem to be a younger kid, you hit adolescence and all of a sudden you decide that in reality
you are ugly and stupid and dumb and everything's wrong about you and you're clumsy and no one likes you
and everyone hates you and you're going to go eat a worm. And I think for most people, even those
who don't have a-
radically extended adolescence.
That feeling in that sensation stays around for a long time.
And in adolescence especially,
it's especially obvious at least.
It'll manifest in this kind of series of
sort of cosplays as potential other use,
or actually as other people who you wish you were
instead of yourself.
You try to look like that person would look.
dress like how they would dress or write the bad poetry they would write. You try to find
some kind of identity other than your own that would be better, less gross. Maybe a post
production, we can get somebody to play a slowed down version of radio heads creep in
the background or something. But that's real. And it continues.
use for a lot of people well into adulthood. The internet is made it easy, right? You
could just full on pretend to be that other person online and hope no one ever finds out.
Even adults though continue to try on these different potential selves other than
themself, these other identities. And part of the problem
with those other identities, right, is that you can't ever actually become that other person
who isn't you. You try and make yourself look like them. You could try and make yourself act
like them, but you're acting, you're cosplaying, you're pretending. When I was six, I wanted to be
Spider-Man. Didn't matter how many spiders I let bite me. I won't gonna be Spider-Man.
But the thing is there is someone better than me, more human than me, more real than me,
who I can actually become and that's Christ.
Of course you know I don't mean I could become another Christ, I don't mean I could become
A God, that's not what I'm talking about.
But who Christ is?
The gospel is that I can become that.
And that doesn't mean ceasing being me.
It means the opposite.
Because when we look at the saints, we see thousands of people who became Christ, who
or formed into the likeness of Christ.
poured into Christ as a mold.
Their identity shaped by his identity, they put on Christ
in their baptism and they lived it out in their life,
taken as a whole.
But each of them is also different
from each other. They lived different lives.
They looked different. They lived in different places
in different times, in different cultures.
They died different deaths.
They lived here.
lengths of time. And it's only in those differences, once we've put on Christ, once we've become
like Christ, it is in those differences, those uniquenesses of the way in which we bring Christ
into the world. That's where we find our actual identity.
That bit, right?
that bit, if I ever were to achieve it,
if I ever were to be fully formed in the likeness of Christ,
that uniqueness, that would be who Father Stephen D. Young actually is.
That would be my actual identity.
So if rather than trying not to be Father Stephen D. Young,
it'd be someone else, right?
who's pretty errands.
smarter and better looking and has better teeth than a nice smile and is loved by everyone
rather than trying to be this fictional imaginary person who ever else I might want to imagine
myself to be.
If what I pursue in my life is Christ, if what I seek to live out in my life is Christ,
then that's where I'll find out who I actually am.
And that's where all those doubt...
about who I am. All those misgivings about who I am, all that shame about who I am, all
that disgusted who I think I might actually be. That's when all that goes away. That's
how someone actually finds themselves. That's how someone actually becomes human. And
I think that, that promise of the gospel, is the core of what we're really celebrating.
The core of the promised...
us, that is given to us by the feast of the offering.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight, everybody.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't happen to give us a call tonight, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsStationsFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voicemail at SpeakPiP.com slash Lord of Spirits.
If you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help
finding a parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And if you're on Facebook, follow our page, join our
discussion group, leave reviews and ratings and all
the appropriate and even inappropriate places.
But most importantly, share this show with a friend who
is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.extravate.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
The podcasters stay on the air.
And folks if you're in the market for a bidet, let me recommend
Hello Tushiba Day System, easy to install. A cold winter morning, absolutely
pracing. Thank you, good night. God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with orthodox Christian priests,
father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported
presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Welcome to another weekly family meditation on...